Guide to the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
Hoover Institution Archives
Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
1903-1991
XX880
Hoover Institution Archives
2772 microfilm reels (340.8 linear feet)
Relates to political conditions in the Soviet Union from 1917 to 1991. Filmed from finding aids and holdings dating from 1903 to 1991 of the Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv sot͡sial'no-politicheskoi istorii.
Kommunisticheskai͡a partii͡a Sovetskogo Soi͡uza.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Original Materials
The original documents are located in three Russian archives:
-Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
-State Archives of the Russian Federation (Gosudarstvennyi arkhiv Rossiiskoi Federatsii - GARF)
and
-Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI).
Related Materials
Portions or the entirety of the microfilm collection may be found at the following institutions in addition to the Hoover Institution: The Library of Congress, Grinnell College, Harvard University, John Hopkins University, University of North Carolina Chapel Hill, Ohio University, University of Washington, University of Melbourne Australia, Glasgow University United Kingdom, Bavarian State University, Germany, and Hokkaido University, Japan.
The microfilms containing only the Russian language opisi or finding aids may be found at the following institutions: University of Illinois, Indiana University, Columbia University, and New York University.
Scope and Content of the Microfilm Collection
This collection concerns political conditions in the Soviet Union from 1917 to 1991. The documents come from three Russian archives. Material was selected for microfilming based on two criteria: (1) records of the highest policy-making units of the Communist Party were the priority; and (2) record series were filmed in their entirety, rather than selecting only particular files or documents (except for some of the Gulag material in GARF) Fond R-9414).
To locate material in the collection, it helps to know that archival documents in the former Soviet Union, and later in the Russian Federation, are arranged in record groups according to the institution that issued or received them. These major groups, which sometimes include thousands of documents, are called in Russian fond (plural fondy). Within each fond the documents are generally divided into smaller groups called opisi (singular opis). opisi are generally organized according to the internal structure of the corresponding institution, but sometimes opisi consist of documents relating to one subject. The Russian word opis has two meanings: (1) a series of documents; and (2) a finding aid. Each opis "series of documents" is provided with a descriptive opis "finding aid." Each opis "series of documents" is further organized into files called dela (singular delo) that contain the documents.
Out of a total of 11,818 microfilm reels, 11,349 reels contain documents and 469 contain finding aids to the fondy available at the Hoover Institution, as well as to some fondy available only in Russia. Each reel of microfilm contains approximately 850 pages, or frames.
The microfilm reel numbers consist of two parts separated by a period, for example 3.427. The first numerical segment is a 1, 2, or 3, identifying the Russian archive source; 1 is RGANI, 2 is RGASPI, and 3 is GARF. The second segment, which is sequentially numbered starting with 1, represents a specific microfilm reel number for that Russian archive.
Scope and Content of the RGASPI Records
Materials described in this document are from the Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI). The collection includes materials from congresses and conferences of the RSDRP-VKP(b)-KPSS and records of the TsK KPSS Central Committee for the years 1917-1990.
There are thirty-nine fonds that were microfilmed for the Hoover Institution at the Russian State Archives of Social and Political History. Thirty-eight fonds consist of one (occasionally two) opis and contain mainly documents relating to the congresses (2nd through 19th; 23rd through 28th) and conferences (5th through 16th) of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (KPSS) [RSDRP, 1903-1917; RKP(b), 1918-1925; VKP(b), 1925-1952; KPSS, 1952-1990]. There are 2,069 files (on 261 reels) in these 38 fonds. All files were filmed for the Hoover Institution.
Fond 17, The Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union records, 1903-1965, 1971, contains documents related to the activities of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party in 1989 and 1903-1917, Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks) in 1918-1925, and All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks) in 1925-1952). The listing below has been prepared for 2,457 microfilm reels of Fond 17. The Central Committee was the leading body of the KPSS, its political, theoretical, ideological, and organizational center. It was elected at the party congresses or sometimes at its conferences. While in power, the Central Committee was the main organ supervising the KPSS, the government, and the political and economic life of the Soviet Union. The main organs of the Central Committee were plenums, Bureau of the Central Committee, Political Bureau, Organizational Bureau, and Secretariat. Decisions mandatory for party and governmental institutions were adopted at the meetings of these organs. The Central Committee of the KPSS also had an apparatus in which one part acted in parallel to the leading governmental structures and the other was dealing with interior KPSS problems.
Arrangement
The collection is organized by the name of the Russian archive that holds the original materials. There are three finding aids for the collection, one for each one of the Russian Archives:
-Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
-Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI)
and
-State Archives of the Russian Federation (Gosudarstvennyi arkhiv Rossiiskoi Federatsii - GARF).
Within Russian institutional archive, the materials are organized into two groups: (1) fondy (record groups consisting of documents); and (2) finding aids that describe each fondy. Fondy are usually subdivided into opisi (series of documents); the number of opisi in each fondy varies.
Glossary
This glossary defines acronyms and names for all three organizations of the microfilming project: the Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI), the Russian State Archives of Social and Political History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsialno-politicheskoi istorii - RGASPI), and the State Archives of the Russian Federation (Gosudarstvennyi arkhiv Rossiiskoi Federatsii - GARF).
ASSR
Avtonomnaia Sovetskaia sotsialisticheskaia respublika
BUND
The General Jewish Workers' Union in Lithuania, Poland, and Russia
Gospolitizdat
Gosudarstvennoe izdatelstvo politichesko literatury
GUITK
Glavnoe upravlenie ispravitel'no-trudovykh kolonii
Gulag
Glavnoe upravlenie ispravitel'no-trudovykh lagerei
GUMZ
Glavnoe upravlenie mest zakliucheniia
IKKI
Ispolnitelnyi komitet Kommunisticheskogo Internatsionala
IMEL
Institut Marksa-Engelsa-Lenina
Komsomol
Kommunisticheskii soiuz molodezhi
KPSS
Kommunisticheskaia partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza
Krymizdat
Krymskoe izdatelstvo
Lenizdat
Leningradskoe izdatelstvo
Malyi Sovnarkom
Malyi sovet narodnykh komissarov
MOPR
Mezhdunarodnaia organizatsiia pomoshchi bortsam revoliutsii
MVD
Ministerstvo vnutrennikh del
NKGB
Narodnyi Commissariat gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti
NKID
Narodnyi kommisariat inostrannykh del
NKPS
Narodnyi kommisariat putei soobshcheniia
NKVD
Narodnyi kommisariat vnutrennikh del
OGIZ
Obiedinennoe gosudarstvennoe izdatelstvo
OGPU
Obiedinennoe gosudarstvennoe politicheskoe upravlenie
Okruzhkom
Okruzhnoi komitet [partii]
Politizdat
Izdatel'stvo politicheskoi literatury
Profintern
Krasnyi internatsional profsoiuzov
PUR RVS
Politicheskoe upravlenie revoliutsionno- voennogo soveta
RKI
Raboche-krestianskaia inspektsiia
RKP(b)
Rossiiskaia kommunisticheskaia partiia (Bolshevikov)
ROSTA
Rossiiskoe telegrafnoe agenstvo
RSDRP
Rossiiskaia Sotsial-Demokraticheskaia Rabochaiia Partiia
RSFSR
Rossiiskaia Sovetskaia Federativnaia Sotsialisticheskaia Respublika
RVSR
Revoliutsionno-voennyi sovet respubliki
SNK or Sovnarkom
Sovet narodnykh kommisarov
SSR
Sovetskaia sotsialisticheskaia respublica
STO
Sovet truda i oborony
Tsentrosoiuz
Tsentralnyi soiuz kooperativnykh obshchestv
TsIK
Tsentral'nyi ispolnitel'nyi komitet
TsK
Tsentralnyi Komitet
TsKK
Tsentralnaia kontrolnaia komissiia
TSU
Tsentralnoe statisticheskoe upravlenie
VChK
Vserossiiskaia chrezvychainaia komissiia
VKP(b)
Vsesoiuznaia kommunisticheskaia partiia (Bolshevikov)
VLKSM
Vsesoiuznyi Leninskii Kommunisticheskii Soiuz molodezhi
VSNKh
Vysshii Sovet Narodnogo Khoziaistva
VTsIK
Vserossiiskii tsentral'nyi ispolnitel'nyi komitet
VUChK
Vseukrainskaia chrezvychainaia komissiia
USSR
Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
Soviet Union--History.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.; Communism--Soviet Union.
Collection Contents
- Finding Aids to All Fondy at RGASPI, 55 reels (Reel 2.1-2.55)
  These Russian-language finding aids were created by RGASPI to describe its 326 fondy. Only the documents in fondy 17, 34-59, 337, 447, 477, 572, 582, 586, 593, 604, 620, 628, and 646 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives.
- Fond 17, The Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union records, 1903-1965; 1971; 2,457 reels
  Documents in opisi 1, 2, 7-9, 75-77, 79, 86, 109, and 139 are available on microfilm at the Hoover Archives. Russian-language finding aids to the documents available on microfilm are:
  Opis 1 on microfilm reel number 2.15
  Opis 2 on reel number 2.15
  Opis 7 on reel number 2.16
  Opis 8 on reel number 2.16
  Opis 9 on reel number 2.16
  Opis 75 on reel number 2.22
  Opis 76 on reel number 2.22
  Opis 77 on reel number 2.22
  Opis 79 on reel number 2.22
  Opis 86 on reel number 2.22
  Opis 109 does not have a finding aid
  Opis 139 on reel number 2.27.
  A microfilm reel list, which provides opis number and English-language title, delo number, and corresponding microfilm reel number, is on pages 21-66 of Finding Aids and Documents from the Three Key Archives on Microfilm (red cover, spiral bound, 130 pages)
  The English-language descriptive list below provides a description of each file, with file number and reel number, for opis 1; and a description of each microfilm reel, with file numbers and reel number, for the other opisi.
  This register has been prepared for 2,457 microfilm reels of Fond 17, which contains documents related to the activities of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party in 1989 and 1903-1917, Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks) in 1918-1925, and All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks) in 1925-1952). The Central Committee was the leading body of the KPSS, its political, theoretical, ideological, and organizational center. It was elected at the party congresses or sometimes at its conferences. While in power, the Central Committee was the main organ supervising the KPSS, the government, and the political and economic life of the Soviet Union. The main organs of the Central Committee were plenums, Bureau of the Central Committee, Political Bureau, Organizational Bureau, and Secretariat. Decisions mandatory for party and governmental institutions were adopted at the meetings of these organs. The Central Committee of the KPSS also had an apparatus in which one part acted in parallel to the leading governmental structures and the other was dealing with interior KPSS problems.
  These materials are held in the Russian State Arcchives of Socio-Political History Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv sotsal'no-politicheskoi istorii (RGASPI). Twelve opisi(out of 158) of fond 17, containing over 11,000 files (dela), were microfilmed for the Hoover Institution.
  At RGASPI, opisi 7, 75-77, 79, 86, and 139 are organized according to the institution's internal structure. Documents pertaining to party censuses are organized geographically and alphabetically (opisi 8 and 9). Opisi 1 and 109 are ad hoc collections reflecting respectively the struggle of the Bolsheviks against the Menshevik opposition within the RSDRP in 1902-1904, and defense of the Soviet republic in 1918-1924.
  This finding aid is arranged by file number (second row of each entry) with reference to the corresponding microfilm reel number (first row). Names of republics are spelled in compliance with American dictionaries. Names of party committees of different levels (raikoms, obkoms, gorkoms, and kraikoms) are transliterated from Russian. The Russian abbreviations for party organs and institutions and for territorial/administrative division of Soviet Russia and/or Soviet Union are used here. They are decoded in the glossary.
  - Opis 1: Records of the Central Committee of The Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party (1903-1905), 5 reels) (Reel 2.56-2.60)
    Opis 1 contains materials related to the activities of the Central Committee of the Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party (TsK RSDRP) (1898, 1903-1917). The TsK RSDRP was elected during the First Congress of the RSDRP in March 1898, but immediately after the Congress its members were arrested. The Central Committee resumed its activities in August 1903, after the Second RSDRP Congress. Its two organs, underground Russian Bureau and the Émigré Bureau of the TsK RSDRP, led practical work of the TsK RSDRP. Three hundred twenty-one files of opis 1 were microfilmed for the Hoover Institution. These files consist primarily of correspondence carried out by prominent members (both Bolsheviks and Mensheviks) of the Russian Social-Democratic Labor Party in Russia and abroad. The documents reflect the struggle of the Bolsheviks for power over the party and its leading organs in the time between the Second and the Third RSDRP congresses. Many of the documents included in this opis have been published [See: Leninskii sbornik, ed. L. B. Kamenev (Moskva, 1925); Perepiska V. I. Lenina I redaktsii gazety "Iskra" s sotsial-demokraticheskimi organizatsiiami v Rossii. 1900-1903 gg. Sbornik dokumentov. V 3-kh tomakh (Moskva, "Mysl", [1969]-1970); Perepiska V. I. Lenina i rukovodimykh im uchrezhdenii RSDRP s partiinymi organizatsiiami, 1903-1905 gg. Sbornik dokumentov v 3-kh tomakh (Moskva, "Mysl", 1974-1977); Perepiska V. I. Lenina i rukovodimykh im zagranichnykh partiinykh organov s sotsial-demokraticheskimi organizatsiiami Ukrainy, 1901-1905. Sbornik dokumentov i materialov (Kiev, Izd-vo polit. lit-ry Ukrainy, 1964); newspaper Iskra, 1903-1904, and other publications.] Files that were published in full are marked with one asterisk; files that were published partially are marked with two asterisks. The main subjects highlighted by the documents in this opis are:
    1. Second RSDRP Congress (adoption of the Party Statute and Program, elections of the TsK and of the editorial board of the newspaper Iskra, relations with the BUND, etc.)
    2. Émigré League of Russian Social-Democracy (the Second Congress of the League, adoption of the Statute of the League, election of the League Administration)
    3. The Bolshevik agitation for the convocation of the Third RSDRP Congress
    4. Relations among the main RSDRP institutions and organs (TsK RSDRP, Party Council, editorial board of the newspaper Iskra, the Administration of the Émigré League, etc.) and between the said institutions and local RSDRP organizations in Russia and abroad
    5. Political, organizational, and financial problems caused by the conflict between the Bolsheviks and Mensheviks
    6. Work of V. I. Lenin on pamphlets, leaflets and essays ["Step Forward, Two Steps Backward", "To Poor Peasants", "What Is to Be Done?", etc.] and pamphlets opposing his works ["Struggle with the State of Siege in the Party" and "Our Congress", by IU. O. Martov's, and "What Is not to Be Done" by G. V. Plekhanov]
    7. Publication, delivery, and distribution of social-democratic literature
    8. Routine party work: dispatch of agents to Russia and their trips abroad, printing and distribution of leaflets, organization of legal and undercover work, escapes of RSDRP agents from exile, personal and financial issues, etc.
    9. Operation of technical institutions of the RSDRP (printing and publishing houses, dispatch office, etc.)
    The finding aid for opis 1 provides a detailed description of each file. Dates are given according to the Gregorian calendar. Russian scholars identified personal names, or part of a name and other data in brackets. Undercover names often used in the correspondence are omitted. The Russian finding aid can be found on reel 2.15.
    - Manifest of the RSDRP (original version of April, 1898, a published brochure of 1903) (Reel 2.56, File 1)
    - Materials (correspondence of V. D. Bonch-Bruevich, I. S. Blumenfeld, and L. G. Deich, financial and accounting documents, salary charts, lists of employees, etc.) related to the purchase of equipment for a RSDRP book-stitching shop, its operation, and personnel, 1903 February-1904 January (Reel 2.56, File 2-7)
    - Correspondence of N. K. Krupskaia, Iu. O. Martov, V. L. Kopp, and others with M. M. Litvinov, with the technical commission of the TsK RSDRP, and others re professional party activities and transportation of social-democratic literature, 1903 June-1905 February (Reel 2.56, File 8**)
    - Letter from L. L. Girshberg to V. A. Noskov confirming the reception of his post-cards and of cash from Geneva and notifying him about the equipment and transport of social-democratic literature, etc., 1903 July (Reel 2.56, File 9)
    - Report on the debts of the book-stitching shop, 1903 after or on August 1 (Reel 2.56, File 10)
    - This file was transferred to Fond 24 in 1970 (Reel 2.56, File 11)
    - Letter from L. E. Galperin to V. A. Noskov re disagreement about transportation issues and about the necessity to organize a conference to discuss the said issues, 1903 August (Reel 2.56, File 12)
    - Draft letter from N.K. Krupskaia to V. V. Vakkar, promising to send literature and explaining difficulties in transporting materials across Russian borders, 1904 March (Reel 2.56, File 13)
    - Correspondence between [V. A. Noskov} and N. K. Krupskaia re secret trip of the delegates of the Second RSDRP Congress to Russia, re states of mind in the party, etc., 1903 August (Reel 2.56, File 14*)
    - Letter from Medvede[v} complaining of not getting letters from an addressee and requesting to pass this letter on to [V. A. Noskov], 1903 September (Reel 2.56, File 15)
    - Article entitled "North-Western Committee or the First Steps of the Party in our Region" (translation from Arbeiter Schtimmer, No. 37), 1904 January (Reel 2.56, File 16)
    - Letter from G. A. Aleksinskii? to the émigré branch of the TsK RSDRP, requesting that party functionaries be sent [to Moscow] and submitting information about the situation inthe [Moscow] organization and about arrests in Orekhovo-Zuevo, 1903 September (Reel 2.56, File 17*)
    - Letter from [F. I.] Dan to [G. V. Plekhanov], re talks about the agreement with former editors of the newspaper Iskra (The Spark), 1903 September (Reel 2.56, File 18**)
    - Letters and claims re the incident in the party printing-office on September 28, 1903, between I. S. Blumenfeld and M. M. Litvinov (autographs of V. D. Bonch-Bruevich, N. K. Krupskaia, I. S. Blumenfeld, M. M. Litvinov, and others), 1903 September-October (Reel 2.56, File 19)
    - Letter from A. A. Shneerson to F. V. Lengnik about the refusal of M. M. Litvinov, chief of the RSDRP dispatch office, to give a seal for the author's passport, and copy of Lengnik's response requesting that Litvinov give a seal, 1903 on or before September 29 (Reel 2.56, File 20)
    - Letter from F. I. Dan to F. V. Lengnik submitting a copy of the author's letter to Plekhanov re negotiations on co-optation of four former editors of Iskra to the editorial board of the Central Organ, 1903 on or before September 29 (Reel 2.56, File 21*)
    - Letters from [F. V. Lengnik] [to the TsK members G. M. Krzhizhanovskii and V. A. Noskov] re negotiations with former Iskra editors, re request from the Mensheviks to establish a literary group, and re struggle against the oppositional majority in the Émigré League of Russian Social-Democracy, 1903 October (Reel 2.56, File 22*)
    - Letters from L. M. Knipovich to the émigré branch of the TsK RSDRP re the issues related to an organizational conference of the TsK RSDRP, the Iskra editorial board, and professional party work, 1903 October-November (Reel 2.56, File 23*)
    - Comprehensive account of the book-stitching shop for work performed for the Émigré League of Russian Social Democracy from April 20 through August, 1903 (Reel 2.56, File 24)
    - Draft letter from F. V. Lengnik to the Russian Bureau of the TsK RSDRP submitting his opinion about Ia. A. Berman, requesting that G. M. Krzhizhanovskii go underground and that [the Bureau] send blank passports to him, presenting information about the failure [of the RSDRP organization] in Kiev, about the contemplated trip of L. E. Galperin to Russia and about Galperin's suggestion to establish a group of managers in the TsK, about TsK finances, about co-optation of M. M. Essen, I. F. Dubrovinskii, A. E. Galperin, and L. B. Krasin to the TsK, about the intention of Martov's supporters' to establish a literary group outside the Central Organ, etc., 1903 October (Reel 2.56, File 25*)
    - Letter from [F. V. Lengnik] to E. Gurevich, member of the group Borba (Struggle), requesting that the latter explain to the members of the group why they were not invited to the RSDRP Second Congress, presenting information about the resolution of the Congress that dismissed the group, and expressing his intention to join the Émigré League of Russian Revolutionary Social-Democracy, 1903 October (Reel 2.56, File 26*)
    - Letter from [F. V. Lengnik] to [G. M. Krzhizhanovskii] protesting the co-optation of M. M. Essen and R. S. Zemliachka and possible co-optation of IU. O. Martov to the TsK RSDRP and explaining the policy toward weakening the Menshevik influence on local RSDRP organizations, 1903 October (Reel 2.56, File 27*)